<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A confession of the most auncient and true christe[n] catholike olde belefe accordyng to the ordre of the .xij. articles of our co[m]mon crede, set furthe in Englishe to the glory of almightye God, and to the confirmacion of Christes people in Christes catholike olde faith. By I.O.</title>
            <author>Old, John, fl. 1545-1555.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113446</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848680</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848680</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1389:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A confession of the most auncient and true christe[n] catholike olde belefe accordyng to the ordre of the .xij. articles of our co[m]mon crede, set furthe in Englishe to the glory of almightye God, and to the confirmacion of Christes people in Christes catholike olde faith. By I.O.</title>
                  <author>Old, John, fl. 1545-1555.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christophor Truthal [i.e. Egidius van der Erve] Cum priuilegio regalj,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Sothewarke [i.e. Emden] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In April. 1556.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.O. = John Old.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; actual printer's name and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apostles' Creed --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A confeſſion of the moſt auncient and true chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like olde belefe, accordyng to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of the xii. articles of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Crede, ſet furthe in Engliſhe to the glory of almightye God, and to the confirmacion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes people in Chriſtes catholike olde faith. By I. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>I beleue and therfore haue I ſpoken.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 10.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The belefe of the hearte iuſtifieth, and the mouthe confeſſeth to ſaluacion.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>☞ <hi>Imprinted in Sothewarke by Chriſtophor Truthal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regalj.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In April.</hi> 1556.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13791:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the vnfayned</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uourours &amp; louers of the pure worde and Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, enha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting within the cities and dioceſe of Couentrie and Lichfelde, and in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, where it hathe chaunced me to haue occupied the rowme of a Preacher: Grace, mercye, and peace (ioyned with earneſt repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and conſtaunt faithe, in the doctrine of the Goſpell) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God the father, and his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon &amp; only ſaueour of the worlde.</head>
            <p>MY moſt ſounng frendes and brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (concerning our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon faith in Chriſt our Lorde) where of late dayes I am contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſlaunderouſly reported, and named among ſome, to be an errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous felowe, one of the new learning, an heretike, one of Latimers ſecte, &amp; I wotte not what: Be it knowen to the worlde, that I am none other, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:2"/>
a true chriſtian man, regenerate &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtructed (nowe in my middle age) in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed ſchole of Goddes moſt holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and Teſtament (thankes be to his fatherly bounteous mercy therfore) &amp; ſythence I haue not folowed the ſecte of any earthy man, nether grounded myne opinion, faithe, or doctrine, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any newe learning or hereſie, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the moſt certaine pure vnfailing true worde, and learning of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, ſent downe, reuealed, &amp; tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght from the ſeate of his Maieſtie, &amp; preached at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement by the fathers and prophetes, by Chriſt his ſonne, and his holy Apoſtles: and alſo regeſtred and ſpecified in the rolles &amp; euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the holy ſacred ſcriptures, to be the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion, rule, and lawe, for the true catholike churche of God to be builded vpon, and ruled by, from the begynning of the worlde, vnto the laſte daye of iudgement.</p>
            <p>And here vpon only haue I ſet the building of my faythe (Ieſus Chriſt hym ſelf beyng the head corner ſtone) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.</note> and according thervnto I haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and faythfully taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed my pariſheners and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as vnto my vocacion I conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb facs="tcp:13791:3"/>
it iuſtlye to apperteyne.</p>
            <p>Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, like as S. paule reporteth, that Apollo &amp; he were mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> by whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s beleued, as God diſtributed vnto euery one: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo doo I acknowlage, &amp; (from the botome of my harte) vnfeynedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that the reuerende father of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memorie Hugh Latimer was to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hugh La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymer.</note> very death a right worthy inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; miniſter of God, by whoſe moſt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine, ſyncere exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of godly lyfe, and conſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t frendſhip towardes me, it hathe pleaſed thalmighty Lord, to open vnto me (among many other the moſt vnworthy) the true chriſtian faithe, &amp; to cal me out of the damnable darkeneſſe of Antichriſtes iniquirie, in to the true light of Chriſtes goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les veritie.</p>
            <p>And like as the people of Berrhoe (by diligent reading and examining <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.</note> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures) fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that Paules doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine was bothe right, true, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly good: euen ſo do I vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly credite, &amp; plainly teſtifye, the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine aſwel of the glorious martir of Ieſus Chriſt, Hugh Latimer (concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng Iuſtificacion, &amp; other articles of the chriſten faithe) as alſo of the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:13791:3"/>
reuerende father in God and right conſtaunt confeſſour of Chriſt Ieſus, Thomas Cranmere Archebiſhop of Cantorbury (concerning the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament <note place="margin">Thomas Cranmer.</note> of Chriſtes precious body &amp; bloud, moſt catholikely and ſyncerely ſet furthe in print) not being ſedde by any carnall affeccion towardes their perſones, nether for worldly promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, but bicauſe I haue perfitly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their doctrine, to be conteyned in the holy ſacred ſcriptures: by teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and waraunt wherof, they and other miniſters of Chriſtes goſpell, haue taught, and ſet furthe the true catholike doctrine &amp; worde of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſaluacion accordingly.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuche as I eſteme them men, which (without ſure holde of the ſcriptures) might both haue deceaued and ben deceaued, therfore I and all other (that be knytte together in one true vnto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and knotte of Chriſtes ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite) laye our foundacion &amp; grounde worke, not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fleſhe &amp; bloud, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no mannes worde (of what power, vertue, wiſdome, learning, au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toritie, eſtate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer he be) but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnfailing true worde of the almightie euerlyuing Lorde God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:4"/>
In the meane while, yf any man can teache me better, &amp; more truly, by the holy canonical ſcripture, I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (as reaſon is) gladly &amp; hartily to folowe him, &amp; willingly geue him pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>digne praiſe, &amp; great gramer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. But as for any other doctrine of faith, beſides the ſcriptures, or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryr to the autoritie of the ſcriptures, either elles by violent wraſting and wrythyng of the ſcriptures out of of their owne ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe, or right meanyng, I ſhall (by the aſſiſtence of goddes mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciful helpe) neuer ſuffre my ſelfe to be plucked awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſimple, plaine apoſtolike true faithe: bicauſe man is frely iuſtified by this ſaith, and euery fayth contrary to this, is a dead frute<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les faithe: &amp; euery doctrine not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to Goddes holy boke <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>Iac.</hi> 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note> the Bible, is to be holde accurſed: yea although it were preached, ſet furthe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by an Angel of heauen, muche more by any mortall creature, thoughe it be neuer ſo great a Kyng, Quene, gouernour, or potentate.</p>
            <p>And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the holy canonicall <note place="margin">The holy canonical Scriptures</note> ſcripture, I (among other poore mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel) hauing charge of ſoule, &amp; folowing the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of other chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churches &amp; teachers, haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:4"/>
&amp; taught my pariſheners and neyghbours, &amp; ſo ſtil beleue and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, on this maner of waye folowing. The canonical ſcripture (I meane the holy Bible) which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true vnfailing declaracion of the eternal wil of God, deliuered by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Gooſt, &amp; preached &amp; diligently declared vnto the worlde (vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde, I meane) by the holy prophetes &amp; choſen apoſtles, is of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the moſt au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient, moſt perfite, &amp; moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctrine, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp; teaching abſolutly &amp; fully, al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarely required to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holſome know lage of God, to true faithe &amp; the true worſhip of God, to true chriſtian righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and to the framyng &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of honeſt, bleſſed, &amp; holy lyfe.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuche as the Canonical ſcripture (the Bible I ſaye) is the ſelfe ſame worde, that the eternal God him ſelfe hath ſpoken and taught, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore endureth permanent, to be a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne vnto the fete, &amp; a light vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes foteſteppes &amp; ꝓcedinges for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: it hath fidelitie, autoritie, certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, truthe, eſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly ynough in it ſelf: ſo as it ought not to be made authentike again by the churche, or by autoritie of the wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men, either yet to be pice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:5"/>
and patched it with the tradicions of men. And albeit mennes ſpirites are not hable to accorde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome bokes &amp; textes of the ſcriptures: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater is not much to be paſſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For we know, that mennes iudgementes ought to be applied and obeye vnto the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not the ſcriptures vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes iudgementes.</p>
            <p>And touching the interpretacion of the holy canonical ſcripture, this haue I thought, and (after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of other chriſten miniſters) I haue taught, and yet ſtil I thinke, and confeſſe vnto the worlde, that it ought <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 1.</note> not, nor muſt be interpreted or expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded after any mannes opinion or thought (much leſſe after euery man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes pleaſure and phantaſie) but by it ſelf, and of it ſelfe, aſwell according to the propreties of the tongues wherin it was furſt written, and by diligent wayeng and conſideracion of the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enges that goo before, and thoſe that be ioyned together and folowe, with all the circumſtaunces: as alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meanyng of other places, that ſeme either more playne, or like ther vnto, or elles contrary: by the lyne and rule of faithe and charitie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:5"/>
And wher the fathers, the doctours of the holy churche haue interpreted <note place="margin">Doctours.</note> and expounded the ſcriptures after this maner, and haue in no wiſe blen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched nor ſwarued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this lawe and rule now before mencioned: them we doo with harte and good will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlage, and take for faithfull and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t interpretours of the ſcripture, and honourable inſtrumentes of the holy gooſt, whoſe paynefull labours and induſtries our Lorde God hathe vſed in the churche, to the glorie of his owne name, and to the profite of his faithfull flocke. And therfore we not only reuerence the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke not well of ſuche men, as haue them in contempt.</p>
            <p>But as for all other doctrines and tradicions of men (how glorious, how gaye, how highe autoritie, title, or au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientie ſo euer they be commended or bragged to be of) if they be not foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon ſome teſtimonies of the ſcriptutes, and alſo if they pull vs from God, from the ſcripture, and from the true faithe, or be hinderous vnto vs in the ſame, I thinke them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vayne, vnprofitable, and of non effecte, yea rather pernicious and
<pb facs="tcp:13791:6"/>
noyſom: as Chriſt him ſelf openly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth of them, Matth. 15.</p>
            <p>Moreouer the only intent, ſcope &amp; ende of the canonical ſcripture is this: that al men of all naciones, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treyes and places might be by it inſtructed &amp; taught, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the grace of God, concerning the redempcion, bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberalitie and ſaluacion, that is pleyntifully beſtowed &amp; geuen in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, vnto this moſt wretched &amp; moſt corrupte ſynfull worlde: &amp; alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning charitie and faithe, namely that the people being now regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, might be partakers of this ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by true faithe, the holy childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God the father, and heires of al his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſtaunce.</p>
            <p>And touching the faithe of Chriſt. I and ſuche other poore ſlaundred Miniſtres haue nother taught, nor doo beleue any other thing, than that is deliuered vnto be from the holy apoſtles, and that we haue receaued of our chriſtian elders and faithfull forefathers. And that ſame I for my parte (ſithence it pleaſed God to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late me from the Antichriſtian darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of popery in to the kingdome of his ſonne) haue conſtauntly and faith
<pb facs="tcp:13791:6"/>
fully kept hitherto pure in euery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion. And the ſame I purpoſe (by the helpe of Chriſtes gracious fauour) to kepe ſtill and confeſſe, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike churche of Chriſt, while the breathe is in my body: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I Beleue in God the father almigh tye maker of heauen and earthe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> And in Ieſus Chriſt his only ſonne our Lorde.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Whiche was conceaued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, borne of the virgin Mary.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> Suffred vnder Ponce Pilate, was crucified, dead, and buried. Be deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in to hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The thrid daye he roſe again from the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> Be aſcended in to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſitteth on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father almightie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> From thence he ſhall come, to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> I beleue in the holy gooſt. </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IX"/> The holy catholike churche, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Sainctes. </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> The forgeueneſſe of ſynnes. </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XI"/> The reſurrection of the body. </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XII"/> And the life euerlaſting Amen. </p>
            </q>
            <p>Now foraſmuche as God hathe geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me grace (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to his mercifull goodneſſe therfore) to pitch my ſtaffe, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion of this moſt holy, moſt
<pb facs="tcp:13791:7"/>
aſicient, &amp; true catholike faith: And to thinke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you ſhal plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly knowe, how I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid articles of my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: I do truly ſaye, &amp; playnly confeſſe, touching the furſt article: that ther <note place="margin">The furſt Article.</note> is but one only, bleſſed, eternal and almightie Lorde and God, in the holy ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, inſeperable, and vnconfuſed Trinitie. God the Father, the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and the holy Gooſt. And what ſo euer is in the nature of thinges aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel viſible as inuiſible, it is well and rightly created and made of God, to the be hoote and profite of man, and by him it is alſo preſerued, beſtowed, and adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>And therfore God is the father of mankind, not for his creating of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde only, but alſo for his daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruacion, eternal goodneſſe, mercie, prouidence, comforting and helping of mankynde.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſeconde Article, I beleue &amp; confeſſe, that God the father, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 2. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note> became a father, not only after he had made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame God was alſo a very father from euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe alſo one onely eternal ſone, eternally begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a diuine &amp; vnſpeakeable maner.
<pb facs="tcp:13791:7"/>
This ſonne of God (I beleue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) is of the fathers owne ſubſtaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and of all one being, of like equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and conſubſtaunciall with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: of all one ſubſtaunce (I ſaye) na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, power, and vertue, and very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Lorde and God, aboue all, in al, and through al thinges.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding we confeſſe the ſonne to be our Lorde, moſt chiefly, for that he hathe deliuered, and made vs free, from the lordeſhip, power, and tyrannye of the deuil: and hauing payde our raunſom with his owne precious blood, which he ſheadde for vs, he hathe made vs his owne pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people: wherof I ſhall ſpeake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde at more large.</p>
            <p>Touching the thirde Article, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and confeſſe, that the ſame ſonne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 3. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note> of God, which eternally hathe ben and is with the father, hathe alſo in this worlde, taken vpon him the very nature of man, of the fleſhe and blood of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed virgin Mary, which was Abrahams daughter, and borne of the ſtocke of Dauid, according to the promiſe of God, declared by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and ſeruauntes, the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and prophetes: and being borne
<pb facs="tcp:13791:8"/>
of her (ſhe remayning and contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtil a chaſte and a pure maide) ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry God and very man, in one inſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſone, without confuſion of the natures of his godhead and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head together, he became like vnto men his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, touching his reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and immortal ſoule, and his mortal body, in al thinges, ſinne only except.</p>
            <p>And after this maner I confeſſe, that he was conceaued very natural man, in the wombe of that chaſte and moſt pure virgin, and of her bleſſed blood, not by the carnal companie of man, but by the holy gooſt: And that he was borne of the ſame virgin, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, howbeit holy and pure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſynne. For all men elles, are (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their owne nature) bothe conceaued in ſynnes, and borne the children of wrathe vnto deathe.</p>
            <p>And in this behalfe I do playnly <note place="margin">Original <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nne.</note> confeſſe original ſynne. For inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as all mankynde (aſwell the infauntes, which haue not yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted actuall faultes, as others of further age) are originally poiſoned <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> with ſinne, and therfore ſubiecte vnto deathe, as the wages of ſynne: from <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 6.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:8"/>
the which ſynne and deathe, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde could not be in any wiſe dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and redemed, but by Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: for that cauſe it was requiſite, that Chriſt, which ſhould put awaye the ſame poiſon, ſhoulde he conceaued and borne holilie and purely without al ſpotte of ſynne, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he might <note place="margin">1. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. <hi>Ro.</hi> 3. 5.</note> offre a pure and a cleane ſacrifice for all, bothe olde and yong, to make vs pure, and free.</p>
            <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the fourth Article. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and confeſſe, that the ſame ſonne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 4. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note> of God and of Mary, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in going about the buſyneſſe and affaires of our ſaluacion, did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly and fully declare the waye of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion here vpon earthe: And that he (to ſhewe vs more certainly, that he is the only Lorde of life and deathe, which is only hable to helpe, and at whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des al helpe muſt be ſought) cured all maner of diſeaſes, ceaſſed the rageing ſtormes of the wyndes and of the ſea, ſuppreſſed the power of ſatan, troade downe all power of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, forgaue ſynnes, and raiſed vp the dead vnto life.</p>
            <p>And after all this, he gaue him ſelf willingly (and of his owne accorde)
<pb facs="tcp:13791:9"/>
vnto deathe. And was ſhamefully and ſpitefully brought furthe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by the Iewes, cruelly torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the gentiles, and laſt of all gilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly nailed vpon the croſſe.</p>
            <p>And here I confeſſe that this ſame our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, very God &amp; very ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuffred (not for him ſelf, but for vs, and for our ſynnes ſake) moſt greuous paynes, vndeſerued ſtripes, and bitter ſorowes: &amp; in his humayne nature (which coulde dye) he was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly dead and buried: &amp; in his ſoule he ſuffred moſt extremely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſharpeneſſe of Goddes iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and the very paines of hel, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might deliuer vs ther from.</p>
            <p>And I moſt faithfully and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleue, that this bleſſed paſſion and deathe of the innocent ſonne of God, <note place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</note> is the only, perfite and eternal righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and iuſtificacion of man before God, and the true ſatiſfaccion, raunſome and payment for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynnes of all the hole worlde.</p>
            <p>And therfore foraſmuche as I am throughly inſtructed in this moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſure ſtrong argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this our true, and vndoubted chriſten ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faithe, I plainly confeſſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:13791:9"/>
man can in no wiſe be iuſtified, pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of his ſynnes, or fynde any ſhifte to ſatiſfie or to be clenſed of them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by any workes or merites of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but only by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free grace of God: that that is to ſaye, by the moſt bleſſed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and giltles deathe of the crucified ſonne of God. And that we are made partakers of the innocencie and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deathe &amp; bloodſhead of Chriſt, at ſuche tyme, as we doo conſtauntly and faithfully beleue, that the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God is our owne: and that he ſuffred that bitter deathe for our ſynnes, to make vs righteous and bleſſed.</p>
            <p>For I will in no wiſe contemne (or recken as of non effecte) the moſt fauourable free grace of God, which opened it ſelf moſt expreſſely &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; deathe of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But I thinke rather verily, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely beleue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that we ſhould openly caſt away, and compt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deathe of Chriſt to be of no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> effecte, in caſe we ſhould ſeke or thinke to be clenſed, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; iuſtified fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſynnes, by any other meanes, than through faithe, by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only bloodſhead, deathe, &amp; rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſom of Ieſus Chriſt: in aſmuche as we heare the holy Apoſtle S. Paule ſaye. I deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe
<pb facs="tcp:13791:10"/>
not the grace of God: for yf righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala,</hi> 2. 3.</note> come by the lawe, than Chriſt dyed in vayne. And alſo: If the enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce come of the lawe, than it is not of promyſe. But God gaue vnto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by promiſe: ſo that they which haue fayth, are bleſſed with faythful Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>As many therfore as in the olde lawe, from our furſt father Adames tyme, vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, were bleſſed and iuſtified, I beleue verely &amp; ſaye, that they were made bleſſed, holy and iuſtifyed through faithe, of free pardon and grace, by none other, but by Ieſus Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed ſede alone.</p>
            <p>Touching the fyfthe article I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſte <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 5. <hi>article.</hi>
               </note> very God and very man, in the ſelfe ſame bodye, that was hanged on the croſſe, and from thence taken downe and buried, roſe agayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead. For althoughe our ſynnes be perfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purged by the Lordes deathe, and a moſt full ſatiſfaction made therby for the ſame: yet hope of lyfe is reſtored vnto vs, and faythe in him is engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in vs, by his reſurrection. For yf he hade not ryſen agayne, we coulde not haue thought, that deathe had ben
<pb facs="tcp:13791:10"/>
ouercome. And ſo we could not haue beleued, that he hade ſatiſfyed for our ſynnes. For deathe is the hyre of ſynne. And death remaynyng in his force, ſynne muſt alſo be thought to remayne. Moreouer Boddes ſpirite and faythe (wherby Chriſtes deathe and merites are applyed vnto vs) be the gyftes of Chriſt rayſed from the deade. Of Chriſt (I ſaye) which hathe waſhed vs cleane from our ſynnes in his owne blood, and ſo is become the propiciacion or mercy ſeate for our ſynnes, and not for our ſinnes only, but for the ſynnes of all the hole worlde: and nowe hauyng dyed for our ſynnes, and being ryſen agayne for our iuſtificacion, he reygneth and trihumpheth ouer deathe. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his very fleſhe &amp; bones, that is to ſaye, his very humayne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with his reaſonable and humaine ſoule, was not deified, that is to ſaye, not chaunged &amp; turned in to his God-head, but only clarified.</p>
            <p>And the clarificacion dothe not conſume, waſte, nor take awaye the propreties of a very humaine body, ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the ſubſtaunce or facion therof:
<pb facs="tcp:13791:11"/>
but only deſpecheth &amp; deliuereth the body and the ſtate of the body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all diſeaſes, whether they be corrupci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or infirmities: that is to ſaye, from feare, dreade, ſorowe, heauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, from all carke and care, from hate, from carnall loue &amp; couetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: from falſe Ioyes and griefes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affections, troubles, ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre, colde, heate, wearyneſſe, and from al maner of infirmities, ſaintnes &amp; ſmerte, and ſpecially from mortalitie and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And on the other parte, it maketh the body and the facion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, cleare, immortal and vncorrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tible.</p>
            <p>Suche a maner of body S. Paules wonted phraſe is to call a glorious &amp; a ſpiritual body: not that it is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde no more fleſhe, nor that it is chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged and turned in to the ſpirite, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> but bicauſe it is no more ſubiecte to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cares or griefes, or to corrupcions, vncleaneſſe, or infirmities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe: and bicauſe it is garniſhed and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with vncorrupcion, immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and many other ſpirituall giftes beſides, out of nombre.</p>
            <p>And like as the body of Chriſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was riſen vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deathe, remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:13791:11"/>
ſtill a very body, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it was become after the reſurrection immortal and glorious: euen ſo ſhall the bodies of all faithfull folke (at the general reſurrection) be made like vnto the body of Ieſus Chriſt, wherof I ſhall ſpeake more largely, in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth article of our faithe. For Chriſt our Lorde (by his glorious reſurrecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the dead) dothe moſt euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proue and declare, that he hathe deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peched ſynne quyte out of the waye, that he hathe ouercome deathe, which cometh by the occaſion of ſynne: that he hathe reſtored life, that he hathe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered hell, for all them that are true faithfull beleuers, and that he hathe mightily put ſathan to flight.</p>
            <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſixthe Article, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and confeſſe, that our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 6. <hi>article.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt aſcended in to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the very ſelf ſame his humaine body, that roſe again from the dead, and ſithence exerciceth not his dominion and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement here vpon earthe, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally. For according to the nature &amp; propretie of his very humayne body, he is in no mo places but in only one, in one ſelf ſame moment.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuche as he hathe caried
<pb facs="tcp:13791:12"/>
our fleſhe in to heauen, &amp; hathe placed it at the fathers right hande, that is to ſaye, in euerlaſting ioye &amp; felicitie, all faithfull beleuers knowe now for a certaintie, that the waye to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is vnſhutte, &amp; ſet wyde open, &amp; that they alſo ſhall (through Chriſt, in whom they beleue) be caried bothe body and ſoule in to euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>For the Lorde him ſelf (with mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.</note> and playne wordes) hathe ſaide: I wil father, that wher I am, ther ſhal my ſeruaunt be alſo.</p>
            <p>Seing than that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body and fleſhe of our Lorde and brother Chriſt, is abyding and reſteth now in heauen, our fleſhe hath this certaine &amp; aſſured hope, that it ſhal be caried thider alſo, &amp; ther (according to Chriſtes promiſe) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.</note> ſhal haue a perpetual dwelling place.</p>
            <p>Further more Chriſt our Lorde ſyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fathers right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that is to ſaye, euen he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is bothe very God &amp; very man, reigneth &amp; hathe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, in like power, &amp; like glorie, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father: ſo as al thinges are in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder his power: &amp; he w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, vpholdeth &amp; ꝑſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth al thinges, &amp; is alſo wourſhipped &amp; ſerued, the vndoubted true &amp; eternal
<pb facs="tcp:13791:12"/>
almightie God. The chief biſhop &amp; moſt high king of al faithfull people ſitteth on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of God. Chriſt Ieſus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only, eternal &amp; faithful true biſhop &amp; prieſt of al true beleuers.</p>
            <p>It is he, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dothe moſt truſtily pleade al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matters &amp; cauſes of his faithfull people, before God his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father</p>
            <p>It is he, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offreth vp all our good wiſhes and faithfull folkes prayers to God the father.</p>
            <p>It is he, that appeareth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually in the ſight of God, prayeng and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king interceſſion for them, &amp; geueth them his bleſſing. And ſo thoſe that be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true faithful belief in dede, wil nother ſeke, allowe, nor receaue any other mediatour, interceſſour, ſpokeſ-man, attournaye, or entreatour, but Chriſt alone.</p>
            <p>He is that only and eternall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and oblacion, which being ones offred for all, endureth for euer, clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctifieth al them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are true beleuers.</p>
            <p>And euen he, this ſelfe ſame high Biſhop and prieſt of ours, dothe daily (w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſpirite &amp; worde) inſtructe &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che his churche and congregacion, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13791:13"/>
geueth them truſty and ſyncere vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right men, to be their teachers and miniſters, whom he alſo garniſheth and decketh with his grace, and moſt excellent giftes, and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth from al euil.</p>
            <p>Vpon Goddes right hande ſitteth Chriſt our moſt roial king, the king of kinges, the iudge &amp; mightie Lorde of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth. He it is, that informeth and ordreth his churche and people, with holſome and good lawes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whervnto they frame and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe all their matters, to the loue of God, and of their neighbour.</p>
            <p>This king of ours beholdeth vs faithfully, and layeth vp all our grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes and ſorowes truſtily in his harte. He is content with good will to heare the complaintes, ſutes and deſyres of all his faithfull flocke, and is neuer wearied nor grieued with the tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them.</p>
            <p>He alſo is that moſt pleynteous fountayne, which alwaies geueth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally and yet neuer wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth, which only filleth, and yet is neuer the leſſe, nor any whitte decreaceth. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ther can nothing at all (no not ſo muche as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes inwarde thoughtes)
<pb facs="tcp:13791:13"/>
be hidden or kept ſecrete. He is the righteous true iudge, iudgeing after thintent and purpoſe of the harte, and rendreth aſwell to the good as to the badde, all that they doo, without all reſpecte of perſones.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that be oppreſſed he relieueth, with his ioyfull and comfortable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour: But as for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſtowte, arrogau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; prowde braggers of their owne powers, whan he ſeeth his iuſt tyme, he is on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bones of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrayght waies, and hurleth them downe and the necke before. Ther is no maner of thing, but he hathe a reſpecte and a conſideracion vnto it. His infinite wiſdome in euery thing and euery where vſeth iuſte and right deſerued meanes.</p>
            <p>He (by his exceding great grace) ſendeth faithfull, truſty and good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be gouernours and rulers. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he directeth and maynteneth in his churche. And contrary wiſe, he dothe ſomtymes take awaye good gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours (as he did lately our moſt chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten king Edwarde the ſixte) and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp naughti and wicked perſones in autoritie now and than (as bloody biſhoppes, proude popiſhe peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:14"/>
&amp; vnnatural merciles forayners) to reigne, &amp; rule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roſt, to punyſhe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trefaicte goſpellers, and worldlinges withall.</p>
            <p>To be ſhorte, Chriſt dothe at all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes defende and kepe thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his be, from their enemies and foes, bothe vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible and inuiſible. After this ſorte Chriſt ſitteth on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of God, and thus is he the only head of his faithfull beleuing people, the only &amp; moſt high biſhop, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt roial &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kyng and prince of them that be his. He is neuer out of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion and company, he is alwaies occupied in the myddes of them, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he nedeth nother the ſeruice, aide, nor aſſiſtence of any vicegerent or helpe felowe. For he is the only and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of righteouſneſſe, whiche altough (as concerning his humayne corporal preſence) he be in one only place in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet he doth worke ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie &amp; frutefully, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his vertue, light, glorie, nouriſhement and power, in al them that be faithfull.</p>
            <p>In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereof, I admoniſhe, &amp; in Goddes behalfe require you (as I haue, accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to mi litel tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alwaies taught my pariſheners, and in other
<pb facs="tcp:13791:14"/>
places, wher I haue occupied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of a preacher) aſwell to pray, and without ceaſſing to call vpon God, through Ieſus Chriſt, and alwayes faithfully to ſet furthe his praiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the doctrine of the holy ſcriptures, as alſo to beware and take hede, that ye make no inuocacion nor praier to the ſayntes departed, for helpe or ſuccour: foraſmuche as to make any moo or any other media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, interceſſours, ſpokeſmen, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours or attournayes to the throne of Goddes mercie, for any neceſſary thing either bodyly or gooſtli, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ieſus Chriſt our alone euerlaſting ſacrificer and aduocate, is the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tranſgreſſion of the furſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, diſhonour to the high maieſtie of God the father, preiudice to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; dignite of Chriſtes euerlaſtig prieſthode, blaſphemous againſt the ſchole learning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> catholike Crede, and contrary to the doctrine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all the patriarkes, prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, apoſtles, euangeliſtes martires, confeſſours, and virgines, that haue any name or comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion either in the olde teſtament or newe, &amp; a plaine
<pb facs="tcp:13791:15"/>
denyall and falſifyeng of the hole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the bleſſed Bible, the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted true holy worde of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſeuenth Article, I beleue and confeſſe, that the ſtate <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 7. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note> of this ſeaſon, and this corruptible worlde, which hathe his beginnyng and was created of God, ſhall haue alſo his ending, and be vtterly deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: and that at the final deſpeche of the worlde, Chriſt our Lorde ſhall in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame body that was wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the croſſe, come vnfailingly in the clowdes of heauen, to iudge bothe the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <p>For at ſuche tyme as the moſt parte of this worlde ſhall layne and holde with the power of Antichriſt, flyrting of the tyme, in moſt horrible conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of bothe God and his worde, and walowing themſelfes in all kynde of ſinne, abominacion and luſt, and ſhal deuiſe and ſet their myndes vpon mocking and perſecuting of them that be true faithful chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleuers: than ſhall Chriſt at a ſodain cheoppe (as it were lightenyng from heauen) com in the clowdes with his holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles vnto iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:15"/>
And the ſame houre, as many as haue died from the begynnyng of the worlde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt ende of the worlde, ſhall by the might &amp; power of Chriſt, riſe ſtrayghtwaye again vnto life: &amp; the other that are not than departed this life, but haue lyued ſtill vnto the laſt daye, ſhall in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or the twincling of an eie, be chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from mortalitie and corruption, in to immortalitie and vncorrupcion.</p>
            <p>And after that, all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al partes of the worlde ſhal be reſtored &amp; gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, and be preſented &amp; ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de before the iudgement ſeate of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; ſhall ſee the iudge ouer their heades corporally, in the ſelfe ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye that he fuffred in. And than the righteous iudge our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall pronounce and geue his laſt and moſt iuſt iudgement vpon al fleſhe, in the ſame maner &amp; fourme, that he long agoo tolde before hande, Matth. 25.</p>
            <p>Than ſhall euery one receaue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their workes. Than as Chriſtes body was at his aſcenſion ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken vp from the mount Oliuete, ſo ſhal they that be faithfull, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> might and power of God, be taken from this
<pb facs="tcp:13791:16"/>
earthe, bothe body and ſoule, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vp in to the clowdes vnto Chriſt our Lorde. Him they ſhall folowe, and with him ſhall they dwell in euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ioye, for euermore continually to abyde. And thoſe that be vnfaithfull &amp; wicked ſhal be deliuered to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil (whoſe cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>piones and houſeholde ſeruauntes they were) to fele and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde (both body &amp; ſoule) ſuche paynes, ſorowes and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as no tongue ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſe, for euer to endure worlde without ende.</p>
            <p>In this behalfe I haue alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought my pariſheners &amp; hearers (&amp; ſo now I require the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> efteſones to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me) to ſet euer before their eies, &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to print in their myndes, that laſt iudgement of God: and with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their former filthy life, to geue themſelues vnto chriſten charitie &amp; good workes. For like as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture dothe clearely and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſhewe, that we are not made righteous, bleſſed and holy, by our owne merites and good workes, but by the only grace of Chriſt through faithe, ſo that all glorie and honour muſt be manifeſtly and plainly aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and geuen to the only fre grace
<pb facs="tcp:13791:16"/>
and pardon of God, and to the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne: euen ſo haue I euer taught, and now (by the waraunt of Goddes moſt holy worde) confeſſe and conſtauntly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this doctrine of faithe is vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable and of non effecte to impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent hooremongers, bawdes, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tones, dronkerdes, oppreſſours, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Idolaters, men pleaſers, epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and other wicked vnfaithful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones. And that this lyuely iuſtifieng faithe is the worker of all maner of good workes (what ſo euer they be) according to the worde of God.</p>
            <p>For he that is iuſtified and made righteous (as faithe only iuſtifieth and maketh righteous) doth liue alſo iuſtly and righteouſly: and iuſtly and righteouſly doth al thinges. And he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dothe faithfully beleue the worde of God, dothe without al doubt percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and knowe, that to be good which God commaundeth, and that to be euil, what ſo euer he forbiddeth. Yea it is the very wonted maner of faithe it ſelfe, to moue and enforce the iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eſchue that is euil, &amp; folowe that is good and right.</p>
            <p>Moreouer he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perfitly &amp; throughly
<pb facs="tcp:13791:17"/>
by faithe vnderſtandeth the mater of mannes ſaluacion and redempcion, bothe doubtles loue bothe God. &amp; his neighbour. And loue is the perfite fulfilling of the lawe: yea in the loue of God and a mannes neighbour he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth al the hole lawe &amp; the prophetes.</p>
            <p>Theſe maner of workes which be the frutes of the ſpirite, faith and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and that we ſhould fall to amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of our life, and what ſo euer the worde of God dothe furthermore commende vnto vs, like as all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preachers and Miniſters doo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently teache and ſet furthe vnto the people: euen ſo they abhorre &amp; reiecte all ſuche workes, as folkes are vſed to fantaſie and deuiſe of their owne braynes, deuocion, or good intentes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary or without the ſure warrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Goddes worde, how vertuous or how holy ſo euer they be eſtemed, or how long ſo euer they haue ben accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed and vſed. For as ſaint Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin ſaithe, Whan the truth is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De vnico Baptiſ. Li.</hi> 2.</note> ſhewed, cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to geue place vnto the truthe. And moreouer he alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth: Let no man preferre cuſtom before reaſon &amp; truthe, for reaſon &amp; truthe do alwaies ſhutte cuſtom out of the dores.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:17"/>
And the holy martir S. Ciprian ſaith alſo: we ought not to paſſe what our elders and fathers that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs did, but muche rather what Chriſt (which was before all men) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs to doo.</p>
            <p>This alſo doo all godly preachers &amp; miniſtres warne the people of: that no man that walketh in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God, and is riche in good workes in dede, ſet his workes in Chriſtes place, nor put any aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aunce, confidence, or truſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though he were made righteous, holy and acceptable vnto God for his workes ſake. For it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only deathe of Chriſt, and free grace and pardon of God, that maketh a man acceptable vnto God, and fitte vnto all good workes: yea to ſpeake truly and plainly, All the good workes that true faithfull people doo, are nothing elles, but a certain free working, that the grace of God enforceth &amp; procureth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all that is ſpoken in the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res concerning the merite and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde that the faithful ſhall haue, ought rightly to be iudged and taken for the grace and free gifte of God. By reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof S Auſti alſo taught,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:18"/>
that all the good workes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full do, are the grace of God, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God dothe crowne &amp; reward his owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites in the faithfull, which he of his bounteous liberalitie reputeth, as though they were our merites, or as though we of our ſelues deſerued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Touching theight Article, I beleue &amp; confeſſe, that the holy gooſt, the thrid <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 8 <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticle,</hi>
               </note> perſone in Trinitie, is the very true &amp; eternal God, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father &amp; the ſonne: &amp; that our Lorde Ieſus now reigneth &amp; adminiſtreth al thinges in his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt, as he him ſelf ſaid: I wil pray the father, &amp; he ſhal geue you an other comfortour to abyde with you for euer, euen the ſpirite of truth, which the worlde can not receaue, becauſe he ſeeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, nor knoweth him. But you knowe him, for he abideth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you, &amp; ſhal be in you. Be ſhal teache you al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, &amp; put you in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of al thinges, what ſo euer I haue ſpoken vnto you. And againe he ſaieth: I tel you truthe, it is expedient for you, that I go away. For yf I go not away, that comfortour ſhall not come vnto you. But yf I goo away, I ſhall ſende him vnto you. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cometh, he ſhal reproue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world of ſinne, of righteouſnes &amp; of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.
<pb facs="tcp:13791:18"/>
Therfore all thoſe that be true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers &amp; miniſters haue plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted &amp; taught their pariſheners &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as I according to my poore talent haue done) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt is not nowe corporally w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his churche here vpon earthe, but that he worketh &amp; reigneth in his faithful flocke, by the holy gooſt ꝓceding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the father and him, and by the ſame ſpirite doth com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte and ſanctifie the faithfull. Al the ioye, all the vertue, &amp; all the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that is in the faithfull, is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God. And without this ſpirite of God, ther is nothing either holy or perfite. Ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al the wyde worlde, that hathe faithe of him ſelfe, but aſwell faithe as al other good gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are of the ſpirite of God: as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apoſtle S. Paule dothe manyfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in many places of his epiſtles teache and make mencion, but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, Ephe. 4. and. 1. Cor. 12. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 9. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the nynthe Article, I beleue &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all they, which truly beleue in Chriſt throughout all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole <note place="margin">what the true catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Chriſtis.</note> vniuerſal worlde, are one body &amp; one church of Chriſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſanctifieth by his holy ſpirite in his own blood. And all they are w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one only bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; knot of
<pb facs="tcp:13791:19"/>
faithe, &amp; through loue vnited &amp; knit to Chriſt, &amp; one to another among them ſelues, lyke membres all of one body: and principally they are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the free grace &amp; gyftes of their heade and ſaueour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This churche is holy, this churche is begotten and borne of the worde of God recorded in the holy ſcriptures: this churche dothe frame and ordre al thynges accordyng to the worde of God: this churche lyueth in chriſten ſobreneſſe and honeſt diſcipline: this churche (alwayes whan it maye, and hauing no neceſſary lette) is partaker of Chriſtes moſt holy ſacramentes, which be two in nombre, Baptiſme &amp; the Lordes Supper.</p>
            <p>From this churche, the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and ſyncere teachers therof do exclude and barre out, nother the vſe of mariage from any ſtate or profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men or women, nor the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ꝓpretie of worldly ſubſtaunce, nether honeſt occupacions or worldly trauailes, ne yet the ordres &amp; degrees of rulers and magiſtrates, nother hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher powers, nor nobilitie, ne yoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, nether bonde nor free, maiſter nor ſeruaunt, nor any ſuche eſtates of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:13791:19"/>
This churche, albeit not many wyſe after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fleſhe, not many great eſtates, nor many noble are choſen membres of the ſame, yet for aſmuche as euery long and nacion vnder heauen, bothe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.</note> of the Iewes and of the gentiles, and ſome of euery ſtate, prayſe the name of the Lorde, from the ryſyng of the Sunne, to the Sunne ſettyng: and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the voice of this churche is heard throughout all the coaſtes of the hole worlde, and (as the prophete ſayeth) hathe ſpread her braunches vnto the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.</note> ſea, and her boughes vnto the ryuers: therfore according to this article, it is ryghtly called the catholike or vniuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſal churche.</p>
            <p>And bicauſe it is begotten &amp; borne <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 1.</note> of the immortall ſede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, mencioned in the ſcriptures, heareth the voice of her head and ſhepeherde Ieſus Chriſt, ſleeth from the voice of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.</note> all ſtraunge doctrines and ſpirites, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be without or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to that worde, and dothe all thynges (lyke an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent wyfe) as her huſbande Chriſt bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.</note> her in his written worde: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it alſo iuſtlye called the holye churche.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuche as the ſupremacie,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:20"/>
iuriſdicion, power, antoritie, lawes &amp; <note place="margin">The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che.</note> doctrine of the biſhop and churche of Rome, be not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon Goddes worde, which the Lordes ſhepe, that is to ſaye, his church and flocke heareth, nor hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nether euer ſhal be heard receaued &amp; obeyed in al tongues &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of true chriſten people, but of a certain folkes in a fewe realmes, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, &amp; people, whoſe eyes ſathan the God of this worlde hath blinded, and bewitched their myndes (among whom Chriſt neuertheleſſe ſcattereth his ſely ſhepe, and defendeth them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadowe of his gracious wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, euen as the he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne dothe her yong chickens) therfore it foloweth many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlye, that the biſhop and churche of Rome with all his ſacrificeing chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layns &amp; other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plices who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer, depending vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or cleaning to the ſupremacie, new &amp; ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lawes, conſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, decrees, tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; cuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of the biſhop &amp; church of Ro. may not be iuſtly called the catholike or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal churche of Chriſt. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche alſo as the ſupremacie, lawes, cuſtomes, canones, decrees, &amp; doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop &amp; churche of Rome (for the moſt parte) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres ar not
<pb facs="tcp:13791:20"/>
borne nor truly grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; immortall ſede of the worde of God, nother do the papiſtes frame &amp; adminiſtre their tradicions, doctrine, religion, ſacramentes, &amp; ceremonies, according to the teſtament and goſpel of God, but vpon the deuiſes, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of men: The teachers &amp; mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of that Romiſhe power, ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie &amp; religion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their membres &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices are falſely called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy church: Bicauſe that churche or flocke of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten ſhepe, wherof Chriſt is the ſhepe-hearde and head, harkeneth to his voice and teaching alone, and folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the voice or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of ſtraunge tradicions, but dothe (concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning the wourſhip and true ſeruice of God, &amp; touching the neceſſarie health of ſoule) only that whiche the Lorde God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth, nother blenching on the right hande nor on the lefte.</p>
            <p>But contrary wiſe, like as the ꝑti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular churches of Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Donatiſtes, Pelagia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Marcioniſtes, Eutichianes, Mahometiſtes, Idolaters, libertines, Anabaptiſtes, and other ſectaries, &amp; fantaſtical ſpirites of errour, be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable malignau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t churche, wherof the prince of this world y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
<pb facs="tcp:13791:21"/>
head. And the teachers &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of errours are by the apoſtle S. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called Antichriſtes: But ſo foraſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>muche as the Romyſhe churche of the ruffling rabines &amp; popiſhe tippet men with their complices the papiſtes, doo not only not founde nor grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de their autoritie, decrees, tradiciones, &amp; doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines (for the moſt parte) vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſure rocke, the worde and goſpell of Chriſt (which, as Chriſoſtome ſaithe, is the only marke to knowe the true church <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Math. ca.</hi> 24. <hi>Ho.</hi> 49. <hi>in opere imperſecto</hi>
               </note> of God by) but alſo in ſome poyntes they wraſte and wrythe, and falſely allege textes of the ſcriptures for their carnal pleaſure and profite, and in the chiefeſt articles of the catholike chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten faithe (like moſt fantaſtical ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of errour, &amp; ſowers of moſt wicked ſectes) they repugne and teache co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the goſpel &amp; ſcriptures of God, altring the immutable ordinaunce of Chriſt, and ſetting vp ſtraunge ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and godſeruice, propounding o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther articles of faithe, and meanes of ſaluacion beſides Ieſus Chriſt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the commaundement of God of non effecte, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their owne traiterous tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciones, &amp; teaching doctrines of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilles, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 4</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:21"/>
as forbidding of meates &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: And foraſmuche alſo as the churche of the papiſtes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not abyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure worde of God, nor to haue it pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vulgare tongue for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes flocke to be fedde withall, but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> baniſhing and ſlaundering the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting teſtament and bleſſed Bible of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ꝑſecuting, empriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, &amp; murthering of the preachers &amp; witneſſes of the ſame, ſet vp their owne gloſes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituciones, cuſtomes, deuiſes, dreames, tradiciones &amp; proce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinges of men, contrary to the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten worde and goſpel of God, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the patriarkes, prophetes, Chriſt, &amp; his apoſtles, and contrary to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding &amp; exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the fathers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue churche: And ſeing moreouer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the churche of the papiſtes had her begynnyng, proceding, continuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, power, aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſucceſſe only by force of wicked Emperours &amp; other naughty princes &amp; traitours, vnder falſe <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>tenſes garniſhed &amp; decked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vſurped name of catholike churche, &amp; other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trefaicte titles, &amp; hipocritical colours: &amp; is alſo mai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tened &amp; vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by treaſon, murther, ſacrilege, fraude, rauine, crafte, ſorcerye, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uring, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:22"/>
lyeng &amp; marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe of mennes ſoules, to vphold their idleneſſe, pryde, crueltie &amp; wyueles hooremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al: I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe &amp; plainly affirme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame ſwarme and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of papiſtes, I meane as many as teache, willingly mayntene, &amp; obſtinately defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macie, tradiciones, &amp; doctrines of the Romyſh religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſetting aſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bible of God, are Antichriſtes: And (amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other erroneous churches of hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief ꝑticular malignau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t church of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil &amp; of al errours: And that the churche &amp; ſea of Rome (according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. <hi>Apo.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 17.</note> deſcripcions of Daniel &amp; Iohn thapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very hoore of Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (wher w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges &amp; pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſpiritual fornicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuppe of her obominaciones) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinful ſynagoge of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed kenel &amp; cathedral churche of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: And alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop of Rome (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame churche) is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſingular great Antichriſt, the man <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note> of ſynne the childe of perdicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the principal aduerſary, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maketh batail w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lambe, &amp; exalteth him ſelf aboue all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called God, ſitting in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God, &amp; vau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting him ſelf to be God, whom the holy apoſtle S. Paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:13791:22"/>
of, 2. Theſſa, 2. &amp; is now (by God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des moſt merciful benefite) reuealed in our dayes, &amp; herafter, the Lorde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the blaſt of his mouthe ſhall deſtroye him &amp; al his littour, &amp; finally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be caſt in to vtter darkeneſſe, to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 24.</note> haue their mede &amp; porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, wher ſhal be weping &amp; gnaſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of tethe, for euer &amp; euer worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ende.</p>
            <p>This mater ſhal appeare more plaine in certain Homilies (intitled Antichriſt) which I haue tranſlated in to engliſhe, and now by the goodneſſe of God, they are put in prynt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. For I promiſe in the ſight of God (he aſſiſting me with the power of his holy ſpirite) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhal be an ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mie, to the vtermoſt of my poore poſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble power, vnto the errours of that popiſhe malignaunt churche and ſata<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nical Romyſhe religion, while I lyue, and after my deathe no leſſe than an enemye.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding like as I neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hurte of any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either in their bodies or their goodes, but by charitie &amp; al gentilneſſe to wynne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe, if it might be, euen ſo I beſeche almightie god, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> botome of
<pb facs="tcp:13791:23"/>
my harte, if it be his godly will, to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be wrapped (through infirmitie and ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) in the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe of popiſhe errours, the light of his pure goſpel, with hartie repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and amendement of their iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to be newe creatures in Ieſus Chriſt, walking in the true frutes of Chriſtes faithe &amp; loue: and as well to doo, as I wolde doo my ſelfe. Amen.</p>
            <p>Touching the tenthe Article, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and confeſſe, that almighty God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 10. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note> by his grace and mercye in Ieſus Chriſt, geueth vnto all true faithfull beleuers free pardon and forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of al their ſynnes (if they will acknowlage and confeſſe them vnto their onely and true gooſtly father God) at what tyme ſo euer they ſhall repent. And this I take to be the true preaching of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>But as for the vnbeleuers, and ſuche as perſiſte ſtil in their vnbelefe and impenitent wickedneſſe, it is not poſſible for them, euer to haue true perfaicte forgeueneſſe of their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And I doo confeſſe, that al ſynnes are not alike, nor after all one condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, but that ſom ſynnes are greater tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome, &amp; ſome ſines more greuous
<pb facs="tcp:13791:23"/>
than ſome: as their maner is to tende againſt the glorie and loue of God, againſt faithe, and the loue of a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes neighbour, ſome more than ſom, ſome leſſe than ſome.</p>
            <p>I ſaie moreouer, that what ſo euer is comitted againſt the lawe of God, that is to ſaye, contrary to the will and worde of God, that ſame is ſinne.</p>
            <p>Wherfore no faithfull preacher or miniſtre dothe make God the author of ſynne, but we declare, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal poiſon of ſynne beganne in the apoſtata of God, and the common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie of mankynde, and in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes owne corrupt will. Howbeit we deme not, but that god thorough his infinite wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ordreth and diſpoſeth mennes ſynnes to his glorie &amp; welth of his choſen.</p>
            <p>And wher I haue learned in the holy ſcriptures, that the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and forgeueneſſe of ſynnes is nother bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed nor bought for any money, or for any other ware or corruptible thing: And ſeing S. Petre did (in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus) bitterly curſe and crye out vpon all them (and their money bothe) which thinke, that the giftes of God maye be bought out for money:
<pb facs="tcp:13791:24"/>
Albeit I ſawe no great occaſion (du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the tyme of my miniſterie) to ſpeake muche againſt pelti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Romiſhe pardones and pilgrimage gates, for the people did abhorre them almoſt of their owne accorde: yet bicauſe the horrible ſuperſticion of the popes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticary ware (which the idolatreus prieſtes vſed afore tyme, and now ſet freſhely a ſale again, in ſtede of hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome medicine to the ſoule, and al for money) is through falſe perſuaſions of couetous lyeng hipocrite prieſtes, through goodly gaye ſhewes &amp; lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kred depe into many peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, eſpecially of olde folkes &amp; ſupſticious wilful wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I declared vnto my pariſheners and neighbours (as place &amp; occaſion of mater ſerued) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iured water, ſalt, palmes, aſhes, ymages, candles, maſſes, diriges, and ſuch other like, being raiſed and ſet vp without &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the worde of god, only of couetouſneſſe, &amp; for filthy lucres ſake, to occupie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rowme, &amp; to claime the merite, honour, &amp; vertue of Chriſtes death &amp; bloodſhead, were not only vayne &amp; vnprofitable dumme ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies, but alſo moſt haynous and damnable ſuperſticion. And in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracion therof I beſought them (&amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13791:24"/>
ſo I doo ſtill) in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; as they wil auoyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peril of their owne damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only to put no confidence, truſt, nor affiaunce in any of them, but alſo to flee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; abhorre them as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt preſent pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purce &amp; peſtilent poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule: And namely that priuate popiſhe maſſe, wherin foraſmuche as the creature is worſhipped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatour, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idole of bread is caried about, reſerued &amp; hanged vp to be gaſed at &amp; worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the ſtede of Chriſt: the prieſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth &amp; drinketh alone: the one halfe of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is nypped awaye front the laye people: their is no publike thankes geuen of the prieſt &amp; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for Chriſtes paſſion. Finally Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes moſt ſacred inſtitucion is altred, defiled, &amp; quyte turned vpſide downe: And ſeing furthermore, that the Maſſe is demed and vſed as a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice propiciatorye: that is to wete, to purchace and geue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes bothe to the quicke and dead, which is the only office, worke, and merite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one only ſacrifice ones offred for all, whan the body of Chriſt was broken, and his precious blood ſheadde vpon the aultare of the croſſe, for the forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueneſſe of the ſynnes of al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde:
<pb facs="tcp:13791:25"/>
Therfore I affirme and conſtauntly confeſſe, that the ſame apiſhe paynted Maſſe is not only vnprofitable and vneffectual to purchace or geue remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes either for the quicke or for the dead, but that it is alſo the dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nableſt idolatrie, and ſuperſticion (as ye maye ſee by the cauſes rehearſed) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt deteſtable defiling of the Lordes moſt ſacred ſupper, the moſt curſed doctrine: the moſt horrible hereſie, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bawdieſt ſpiritual hooredome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer ſathan inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to breake faithe, loue, &amp; knotte of mariage betwene Chriſt the huſbande, and his ſpouſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flocke: the greateſt preiudice to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignitie of Chriſtes croſſe &amp; paſſion, the maintenaunce and chief keye of Antichriſtes curſed kingdom, the prieſtes chief marchaundiſe and money marte: &amp; finally, the deuilles owne yole game or entrelude. For as Bede in rehearſing S. Auguſtin vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 1. Cor. 10. ſayeth: <hi>Quid luſui puerili magis Simile eſt, quam idola colere?</hi> what is more like a boyes game, than the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of ydoles? What cuckoldrye that curſed Maſſe cauſeth, what for nicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it enticeth, what careles life it occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioneth, what idleneſſe and miſchief it
<pb facs="tcp:13791:25"/>
mainteneth, what vngeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God it prouoketh, it were to long to make rehearſal at this preſent, yea it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not poſſibly be expreſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tongue or pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.</p>
            <p>Therfore aſſure your ſelfe, that like as if a man thruſt his body and his clothes in to a fornace of hotte ſcaldi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g pitche, he ſhall marre his clothes, and put his body in peril of deſtruccion: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo he that thruſteth him ſelf in to the preſence, worſhipping or hearing of the maſſe, and other popiſhe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiones, marreth his new garment Ieſus Chriſt, as muche as in him lyeth, and putteth him ſelf bothe body and ſoule in perile of perpetual dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion.</p>
            <p>And as euery honeſt harted huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande wolde not only be aſhamed of his wife, but alſo (onles ſhe repented) put her out of his companye for euer, if ſhe were bothe an harlot of her ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and a common bawde, to ſtande by wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her neighbours wyues were defiled alſo: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo our ſaueour Chriſt being the head and the huſbande of all the hole chriſten congregacion, is aſhamed, offended, diſhonoured and angred, whan any man or woman kepeth company with that hooremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb facs="tcp:13791:26"/>
maſſe, or ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth by, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other chriſten people are de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filed with it.</p>
            <p>If a gelous huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de can not abide to haue his wife to be kiſſing &amp; famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other men: Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre that the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie ſtrong gelous Lorde God can not abyde to ſee his wyfe the chriſten flocke, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit hooredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before his face w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Antichriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſcheuous maſſe. Awaye, awaye (ſayeth the prophet) get <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 52.</note> out from thence, you that beare the veſſelles of the Lorde. The veſſelles ſignifie not only your ſoules, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo your bodies, which ye ought to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe and kepe in holyneſſe &amp; honour: <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> bycauſe they are the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of Chriſt, and the temple of God. Who ſo euer defyleth the temple of God, the Lorde ſhall deſtroye him. For the temple of the Lord is holy, which ye are. Seing than you belong holly vnto Chriſt (aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well body as ſoule) and that you haue no power of your ſelues, being the ſpauſe of Chriſt, and the very temple of God, wherin the holy gooſt maketh his dwelling: what a doo hathe the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God wyth Idoles?</p>
            <p>Take hede therfore in tyme. For though God of his merciful benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:13791:26"/>
did beare with vs in the tyme of ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noraunce, yet we maye not loke, that he wil do ſo nowe in the tyme of ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne wilfulneſſe, ſeyng the light of his glorious goſpel is ſpread ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore al our eyes, ſo that no prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe nor excuſe in that behalfe wil be pleadable at the barre, before our moſt iuſte iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and gelous huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I knowe wel ynough, it is as hard a caſe as Suſannes caſe was. But foraſmuche as it is a mater (in myne opinion) bothe vndiſputable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſable, our beſt ſauegarde is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne our owne carnall reaſons, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte al to the prouidence of God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng with Suſanna: It is better for me to fall into the handes of men without the dede doing, than to tranſgreſſe the lawe of the Lorde my God.</p>
            <p>In ſhe (wil ſome ſaye) God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful. It is true. His mercie is on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare him, throughout al generaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But wittingly and willingly to heape ſynne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne, in hope of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des mercy, is moſt ſhameleſly to abuſe the goodnes of God, and ſtampe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote the graces of his ſpirite, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hardneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can not repent, to laye wrathe together in
<pb facs="tcp:13791:27"/>
ſtoare againſt the daye of wrathe, at the open declaracion of the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, which ſhall rendre to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one, according to this dedes.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles I ſay not this, to dryue myne olde neighbours and countrey men in to deſperacion, for ſetting vp or hearing of that wicked Maſſe, but to moue them vnto earneſt repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; to powre out their continual hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble hartie praiers &amp; greuous gronynges before the throne of Goddes grace, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel for pardon of their deſerued euil, as for the repulſe of this maſſing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief out of the realme: &amp; to thintent thei may alſo haue a good hope of god des mercie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he for his ſonne Chriſtes ſake, will defende and deliuer his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted flocke, by ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doughty Daniel, as he did Suſanna, according to his promiſe by the prophet Dauid: Now for the comfortles troubles ſafe of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal,</hi> 12.</note> nedy, and bicauſe of the depe ſighing of the poore, I will vp, ſaithe the Lorde.</p>
            <p>Alas wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ther more comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les trouble? Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ther more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de? Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ther more cauſe of depe ſighing, than now? Repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therfore for Goddes ſake, repent and praye.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuche as we nother
<pb facs="tcp:13791:27"/>
knowe nor acknowlage any other <note place="margin">Purgatory</note> purgacion or purgatorie clenſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye of ſynnes, but only the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, I haue euer taught, and ſtill doo affirme, that the ſoules of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be departed this life, are pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or ſcowred no where elles, nother in any purgatory fire nor popes ſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding houſe: but I ſaye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the powches of them that be alyue are rather emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied and ſcowred by purgatorie purga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, through theſe falſe lyeng licke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peny dreames. A faithfull mannes ſoule, as ſone as it departeth from the body, go the ſtraight to heauen, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnfaithfull mannes ſoule ſtraight to hell: as it ſhall anon be declared more plainly.</p>
            <p>In like maner the religious life of cloyſtre men and women is not to be compted meritorious for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion <note place="margin">Cloiſtre re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion.</note> of ſynne, nor among the ſtates of an holy life (as it is vſed vnder the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie) but rather an idle ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and an Antichriſtian life, a very enemye to the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and doctrine of Chriſt and his apoſtles, and good for no honeſt vſe in the common weale, as their filthy dedes fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges viſitacion are not yet out of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:28"/>
Concerning the eleuenth Ariticle, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 11. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note> I beleue and confeſſe, that theſe our bodies, wherin we doo worke in this worlde, either good or euil, ſhal ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne from the deade, and non other for them, nor in their ſtede, that is to ſaye, that this ſame fleſhe of ours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rayſed vp at the later daye, ſhal by the power of God, riſepfitly in dede: and that dead folkes ſoules being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their raiſed bodies, ſhal-be ioyned and coupled to them again: &amp; that all maner of folkes (be the good and badde) ſhall ryſe and appeare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordig to S. Paules ſayeng: We muſt <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> nedes be all preſented before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment ſeate of Chriſt, that euery one may receaue the workes of his body, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that he hathe done in the body, whether it be good or badde. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe the righteous ſhall after thexam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their head Chriſt, be gloriouſly clarified in their bodies vnto vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupcion, eternal lyfe, and euerlaſting ioye, that no tongue can expreſſe.</p>
            <p>Than ſhal the righteous ſhyne lyke the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in the kingdome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father: where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary wyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnfaithfull fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſhall not be clarified, but ſhal be
<pb facs="tcp:13791:28"/>
made immortal &amp; vncorruptible, that they may endure eternal ſorowes, pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, heauyneſſe, &amp; tormentes, worlde without ende. But this reſurreccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the dead ſhal be in the laſt daye, whan our Lord ſhal come (as we ſaid before) to iudge bothe the quicke &amp; the deade.</p>
            <p>Finally as to the .xii. Article, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue &amp; confeſſe, that after this our tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitorie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The.</hi> 12. <hi>Article.</hi>
               </note> lyfe, ther ſhal an eternal &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting lyfe folowe, which God of his owne mere grace &amp; fauour prepared for mankynde before the beginning of the worlde, &amp; hathe promiſed it in Chriſt to al them that be faithful, and wil bothe truly &amp; faythfully performe &amp; beſtowe it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful perſone departeth, his ſoule goeth nother into any iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fire, ne into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaughterhouſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maner of payne, nother doth it fall on ſiepe (for it can not ſlepe) nor dyeth t the bodie (for it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not dye) but only it departeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, &amp; is by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Chriſt take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp &amp; receaued into euerlaſting ioye &amp; bliſſe. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe, almightie god of his iuſtice hath <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>pared &amp; ordained after this lyfe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, eternal &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting payne, eternal torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13791:29"/>
ſorowes, &amp; euerlaſting da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion for al them, that are vnfaithfull and can not repent: ſo that whan an vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſon dieth out of the fauour of Chriſt, and periſheth in his ſinnes: his ſoule alſo (as ſone as it is out of the bodie) is ſtraight caried to hell, and put in to euerlaſting ſorowes and tormentes.</p>
            <p>And albeit the vnfaithfull mannes ſoule ſhall at the reſurreccion of the dead returne to his bodye, and be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned again vnto it, yet it ſhal be dryuen away with the body and with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil him ſelf, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſight and preſence of God, in to euerlaſting paynes, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the faithfull people ſhall at the laſt daye be receaued bothe bodye &amp; ſoule, in to euerlaſting ioye. Amen.</p>
            <p>Lo, my good brothren and louing frendes, This is my belief, this is my faithe, this is the pith and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief &amp; moſt maters that I euer taught among my pariſheners and neighbours, during the tyme of my miniſterie.</p>
            <p>And I am ſure that this is no new fangled nor erroneous doctrine, neither any ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of hereſie, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt vndoubted true, &amp; the very catholike
<pb facs="tcp:13791:29"/>
chriſten faithe, and the moſt auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſubſtauntical learning and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, beleued and preached by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and apoſtles, as they receaued &amp; learned it, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde God him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And although tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes and papiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes with other phantaſtical ſpirites of errour, do conſpire, conuent, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, empriſon, racke, &amp; rage neuer ſo craftily, neuer ſo maliciouſly, neuer ſo ſlaunderouſly, and neuer ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly againſt the preachers and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of this faithe, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil him ſelf and the gates of hell ſhall neuer preuaile againſt it.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſeing it hathe pleaſed our moſt mercifull God to geue vnto me (moſt vnworthy wretche) his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light of this faithe, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar charge in this miniſterie: Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering alſo, that Ieſus Chriſt wolde not, that the candelles appointed to ſerue his houſeholde with their light, ſhoulde be ſhoued vnder a buſhell, but be ſet openly vpon a candleſticke, to geue light to all them, that be in the houſe: I thought it my duetie in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to put you in remembraunce of the true chriſten catholike faithe, nowe in theſe daungerous dayes of
<pb facs="tcp:13791:30"/>
perſecucion by writyng, which I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto you in open doctrine, to the comforte and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo many as contynue ſtedfaſt beleuers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient folowers of the ſame.</p>
            <p>At y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hooded chaplaines of Antichriſt, not only wolde not ſpeake ones againſt my doctrine, either in Lichefelde, Couentrie or elles where, but alſo allowed it, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked god (in wordes at leaſt) for it. And ſom offred me for my paynes money and large rewardes, which I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke God, I haue kept my handes cleane from, yet hitherto, as I reporte me to their owne conſciences.</p>
            <p>At y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme they confeſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues throughly perſuaded &amp; manifeſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicte by the only ſtreynght &amp; power of Goddes ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worde, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And ſo were they cheariſhed, and louingly vſed, &amp; intreated w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all lenitie and ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilneſſe, not ſuſteining the loſſe of one halpeny of their lyuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, nor trouble of their bodies, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poynt of religion. But what chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilneſſe is ſhewed now a daies vnto ſuche poore miniſtres as be in my caſe, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what face &amp; ſtreinght of ſhameles lyes &amp; merciles tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny they
<pb facs="tcp:13791:30"/>
defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de their popiſhe pedlarie &amp; drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie dregges of Antichriſtes alelomes, God knoweth, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I committe both my ſelfe &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of my doctrine: which neuertheles is not mi doctrine, but the doctrine of al the true catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churche, which I haue (by goddes pleynteous mercie) ſucked out of her ſpiritual pappes by faithe, wherby God hathe made me hable now, thus to vttre and ſpeake.</p>
            <p>To be ſhorte at a worde, I ꝓteſte &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly affirme in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knoweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoughtes of all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</note> men, &amp; of his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſt, which is ordained to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudge bothe of the quicke &amp; of the dead, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I neuer taught nor preached any thing vnto my pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheners or elles where, touching any of theſe Articles aforeſaid (during the tyme of my miniſterie by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence) but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſwell I was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den (by force of my miniſterie) to preache and teache in payne of my da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as alſo my pariſheners &amp; hearers to beleue &amp; doo after, in payne of their damnaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wherfore I pronounce with the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note> holy apoſtle: If any man preache any other goſpell, than that we haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and taught, curſed be he.
<pb facs="tcp:13791:31"/>
Seing than, that Chriſte taught and ſpake among them by me, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not eſteme that maner of ſpeaking &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching (though it were homely and plainly) as the worde or ſpeche of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but (as it was in dede) the very worde goſpel, &amp; voice of Ieſus Chriſt, which is not only the power of God to ſaue <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.</note> al that beleue, but alſo the thing wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by euery one of vs ſhal be iudged, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great daye of reckonyng.</p>
            <p>Seing alſo that the true preachers of Chriſtes goſpell (among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God of his mercie appointed me to be one) are a good ſauour vnto God, bothe in them that are ſaued and in them that periſhe: in them that periſhe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauour <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> of deathe vnto deathe, and in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſaued, the ſauour of life vnto life: I beſeche you for the vnſpeake able mercies of God, &amp; as you tendre the ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your owne ſoules, caſt not awaye that moſt pleaſaunt heauenly poyſye of the ſwete ſmelling goſpel of God, but holde it harde to the noſe &amp; ſenſes of your ſoules, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſtynking carion of Maſſes &amp; other filthie foile of blaſphemous popiſhe idolatrie and wicked life poiſon you not vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deathe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:31"/>
Geue no credence to thoſe idle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied buſſarde biſhoppes and prieſtes, <note place="margin">wethere cocke bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes &amp; prieſtes.</note> which in bleſſed ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Edwardes daies, ſemed to be fauourours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, &amp; furtherours of the kinges pcedinges (as they termed it) and now for their owne filthy gaynes ſake &amp; pleaſing of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ſhutte vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorious goſpel of Chriſt) before men, nother entring in them ſelues, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maith.</hi> 23.</note> nor ſuffring them that wolde, but ſom of them (contrary to their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) perſecute it: and yet for cake &amp; pudding wolde turne again (like we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thercockes) which waye ſo euer the wynde bloweth, as a man will haue them: and being blynde guydes, take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to leade the blynde, vntil both fall in to the dike of ppetual da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Deceaue not your ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of your forefathers &amp; elders, <note place="margin">Elders.</note> which were conceaued and borne in ſynne, &amp; brought vp in ignoraunce, as well as you: but rather doo after the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the pure ſpottles lambe of God, Ieſus Chriſt, which was before your fathers, and is the very eternal truth it ſelf, as ye hearde before, by S. Auguſtin, and Saint Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priane.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:32"/>
Folowe not the facio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike worlde, nor the raſhe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude. Ephe.</hi> 4.</note> trade of the madde multitude, which walke in the vanitie of their owne mynde and not after Chriſt, nor in the conſideracion of any iudgement to com: but rather be you renewed in the ſpirite of your mynde, and put on the new man, that after God is made through righteouſneſſe and true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe: conſidering that all our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and veracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are the rodde &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reccion of our moſt louing heauenly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> father God, that we ſhoulde not be damned with the wicked worlde.</p>
            <p>Be not carefull for meate, clothe and wealthe of the worlde, either for <note place="margin">Care of worldly ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</note> your ſelues or for your wyues, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren or familie: but ſeing the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie eternal God him ſelfe is the father of the fatherles, and the prouider and defendour of the widowe: and ſeing alſo he forſaketh not the godly, nor ſuffreth the righteous mannes ſede to begge their bread, but openeth his hande, and filleth euery lyuyng crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the largeſſe and pleyntie of his bleſſing: caſt all your care vpon Chriſtes backe, which ſhall fede your ſede and houſeholdes, and ſhall neuer
<pb facs="tcp:13791:32"/>
ſee the righteous lefte deſtitute.</p>
            <p>Drede not the daungerous tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <note place="margin">Tyrannes</note> of Antichriſtes ſouldiours, nor the bragging othes or chittre chattre po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g pye, or any ſuch other, ſeing the nature of that kynde of bir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haunteth not hennes neſtes for loue of the henne, but to fill their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies with the yolke of her egges: and ſeing that all the heares of our head are nombred, ye may be aſſured that they ſhal doo no more againſt vs, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theternal purpoſe and hande of God hath determined. For God is faithful which will not ſuffre vs to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted aboue our habilitie, but ſhall geue vs a waye out with the temptacion, that we maye be hable to abyde it.</p>
            <p>Be not afraide brethren, Goddes iron rodde is as ſtrong to beate them backe, as euer it was. He that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in heauen, laugheth them to ſcorne, and will combre their ſtomac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes one daye, ſo ſore, that they ſhall not knowe which waye to turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let them runne on (their rageing race) vntil they bring them ſelues out of breathe.</p>
            <p>And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other parte, Fyre, fagot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, hempe, galowes, ſtockes, fetters,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:33"/>
&amp; priſon make vs like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage of the ſonne of God, and the ſuffring of deathe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpelles ſake, is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.</note> of that is behinde of the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones of Chriſt in our bodies, to beare witneſſe againſt tyrannes and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked papiſtes, and to be an example and encourageing of the hole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion.</p>
            <p>The deathe of ſuche as ſuffre for the goſpell, is ſo precious in the ſight of God, that it is the ende of al troubles and ſorowes, and the begynnyng and entraunce of ſuche ioye and treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as no eye hathe ſene, no eare hath <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> hearde, nor any harte is hable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue. This is moſt certainly true, which as it is eaſily ſpoken or writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but very harde for the cowardly fleſhe to beleue it, or to thinke on it, whan the very pynce of trouble and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucion cometh (as I knowe by myne owne fearful experience ynough and to muche) euen ſo I beſeche God to lighten our hartes and remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with his holy ſpirite, that whan the howre and fytte of ſorowe and veracion cometh, we maye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, willingly, &amp; ioyouſly laye the croſſe on our ſholders, &amp; marche forewarde
<pb facs="tcp:13791:33"/>
luſtyly to the batail, that is pitched againſt vs, folowing the ſame trace, that our captain and ſaueour Ieſus Chriſt hathe ledde vs the waye, ſo as by many tribulations, and the ſtraite <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> waye, which fewe fynde, we maye entre in to the kingdom of heauen, and receaue the crowne of eternal glorie that neuer ſhall fade awaye.</p>
            <p>And be not deceaued (my brethren) with the doublefaced doinges, and toyeng trades of thoſe politike, ſubtil, ſleightye wiſe men and nyggardly nyppe cruſtes, which lyke as they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and haue ſet vp the Maſſe, with al diligence: ſome not only for aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cuſtome and opinatyue deuoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones ſake (as draffe is good ynoughe for ſwyne) but alſo for pretenſed obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and nien pleaſing, regarden the maſſe (which is the deuilles inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and the workemanſhip of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt) more than they doo the ſyncere worde and ſacramentes of God, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred according to Chriſtes owne inſtitucion: ſo doo they loue and care more for their faire Abbeyes, &amp; riche wealthe of eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſiones, than they doo either for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe or for any other religion, as by their fyne
<pb facs="tcp:13791:34"/>
frutes (if they were forced to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtritucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) it wold moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly appeare, for al their deuout maſſe hearing.</p>
            <p>But aboue al other, abhorre &amp; bliſſe you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the participacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Diuorced prieſtes.</note> kynde of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable dryuelles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes, which (in king Edwardes tyme) cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled them ſelues in mariage, ſom to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of popery, ſom to hyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhame of their filthy doinges, ſom for men pleaſyng, ſom to do as other did, ſom for one reſpect, ſom for an other: And nowe (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doctrine of deuils is ſet vp againe, &amp; the popiſhe powers of the world fauour not that chaſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of lyfe) theſe dryuelles not only ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe their faithleſſe heartes in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the inſeperable knotte &amp; bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of lawful mariage, forſaking &amp; caſting of their wyues: wherby it is euident, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their intent was only to couer their fleſhely hooriſhe luſtes with the clooke of mariage, without any inwarde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to lyue in a chaſte maried lyfe, but alſo (to ſhewe them ſelues y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nu.</hi> 21. 2. <hi>Pe.</hi> 2.</note> ſucceſſours of Balaam the ſonne of Boſor, and to make their blaſphemy and damnacion more notorious) they renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, recant, and abiure their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, at Antichriſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:
<pb facs="tcp:13791:34"/>
and lyke damned dogges (whom the eternal burning galowes of hell gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne for) they are returned to their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite of maſſing and other Romiſhe religion, crucifyeng afreſhe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebre.</hi> 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12</note> a mocke of the ſonne of God, &amp; moſt ſhameleſly blaſpheme the holy gooſt, wherof they ſhal be forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this worlde nor in the worlde to come.</p>
            <p>Let them take their tyme whyle it laſteth, for ſeyng they haue forſaken to be the membres of Chriſt, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng they are made the membres of the harlot of Rome, and become the temples of ſathan, to beare hell about with them, and to glorifie the deuil in their bodies and in their bodily doin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Their finall damnacion is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely at hande. At that tyme they ſhall knowe, that it had ben better for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue ben made lyke vnto the yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of Chriſt, in ſuffring the loſſes and reproches of the worlde for a littell whyle, and ſhortlye after to be made partakers of his glorious reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; eternal bliſſe, than for a litel beaſtly bely cheare (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal ſone haue an ende) to ſuffre afterwarde perpetual paines
<pb facs="tcp:13791:35"/>
and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes with their predeceſſour Iudas Iſcarioth world w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ende.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles I wiſhe them repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce euen from the very botom of my hearte. Nether doo I ſpeake this vpon any diſpleature or vncharitable affeccion conceaued agaynſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes perſon or worldly quietnes, but only that it greueth the very harte roote of me, to ſee the inſtitucion of God ſo horribly diſhonoured, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſtate of mariage ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſlaundred, the congregacion of Chriſt ſo greuouſly offended, the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Antichriſt ſo beaſtly obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the holy gooſt ſo deſperately blaſphemed.</p>
            <p>Alas, why doo they not conſidre, how haynons a ſynne it is, to geue ſuch an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre &amp; ruine to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God, &amp; how ſmal a gayne it is to wynne a ſmal pelting ꝓmocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of worldy liuing for a ſhorte ſpace, &amp; to caſt awaie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> price of Chriſtes precious blood, in vtterly da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng their owne ſoules, &amp; bequeathing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the deuil for euer more. For if Baalams mortal blynde aſſe rebuked y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> blynde ꝓphetes folye, muche more ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal worme of theſe Aſſes (nay Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſes)
<pb facs="tcp:13791:35"/>
conſciences rebuke &amp; accuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their blaſphemie &amp; ſhameful ſlydig from the truthe, at ſuche tyme as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they ſhall curſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were borne in, &amp; the very howre wherin they were begotten. Theſe men be of that company, vnto whom the holy gooſt biddeth vs not to ſaye ſo muche, as God ſpede: nether to eate nor drinke with them.</p>
            <p>Finally good brethren, be not par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers <note place="margin">Maſſe hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring goſs pellers.</note> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example and faynt carnal excuſe of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaye, although they goo to the churche and be preſent at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe, yet they worſhip none but the lyuing God in their hartes, &amp; hate the Maſſe as muche as we do. Which ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng is muche vnlike to be true, but ſemeth rather a vayne pretenſed fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, and prepoſterous wraſting of ſome textes of ſcripture, wherwith the Deuil deludeth the ſenſes &amp; ſoules of many tendre carpet goſpellers, at this preſent tyme of tryall, to bring them paſt repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunce. For Chriſt our ſaueour ſaithe: No man can ſerue two maiſters. So it foloweth, that foraſmuche as the body (which is the one parte of a man) ſerueth the deuil: the ſoule (which is the other parte, and
<pb facs="tcp:13791:36"/>
ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not poſſibly ſerue God. For God requireth the hole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſerue him, with all the ſoule and powers of man, or elles he reckoneth it not only for no ſeruice at all, but alſo taketh it for very enemytie. And therfore he ſaythe: He that is not with me, is againſt me.</p>
            <p>The body go the not to Maſſe with out the company and conſent of the ſoule. And therfore it muſt nedes be graunted, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule is caryed with the body to ſerue the deuil at Maſſe, &amp; not the body caried awaye by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule from that moſt ſtinking idolatrie and ſuperſticion, to the pure ſeruice of God.</p>
            <p>Bicauſe Chriſt died for theternal ſaluacion aſwel of the body as of the ſoule, the holy gooſt commaundeth vs alſo, to beare and glorifie God in our bodyes, and that euery one ſhould poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſe <note place="margin">The gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Maſſe.</note> and vſe the veſſel of his body, in holyneſſe and in honour. And to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe our bodies vpon the ſeruice or preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynfull filthie Maſſe, is not to poſſeſſe the veſſell of the body in holyneſſe and honour, but to defile the hole man with filthyneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtie, to breake wedlocke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:13791:36"/>
our huſbande, to offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the weake for whom Chriſt died, to comfirme the wicked in their popery, and ſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the vengau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe the body and the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Saint Iames ſaithe, that a double mynded man is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtaunt in al his waies, and maye not loke to obteyne any thing of the Lorde, wher ſo euer he praieth: muche leſſe wil God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his peticiones, which he makteh in that temple, wher God by the ſame pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticion makers preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is diſhonoured, and the congregacion (which is the right temple of Chriſt in dede) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed.</p>
            <p>The ſcriptures teache vs, that at the great iudgement, euery one ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue according to the dedes that are done by the bodie. And at the general reſurreccion, the body and the ſoule ſhal be ioyned together, perpetually to abide either ioye or ſorowe: ſo that the bodye muſt nedes goo to hell for defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it ſelf with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abominable Maſſe and other popery: And the ſoule can not choſe, but goo with the body, and take ſuche parte as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body dothe. For God wil not parte ſtakes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuill.
<pb facs="tcp:13791:37"/>
Therfore it is but a vayne pretenſe and a very mocking of God, to ſaye, that the harte and ſoule ſerueth God, ſeing the body ioyned with the ſoule ſerueth the deuil in the ſight of God and men. So it ſemeth manifeſt, that ſuche goſpellers, as be maſſe hearers, are not ſpiritual goſpell folowers, but carnall goſpell ſlaunderours, and walke after the fleſhe: vpon whome the holy Gooſt geueth ſharpe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, ſayng: Yf ye lyue after the fleſhe, you ſhall dye.</p>
            <p>Conſidre brothren, that we are now after our ſyncere goſpelling, ledde of the holy gooſt in to wilderneſſe (as Chriſt was after his baptiſme) to be tempted of the deuil. Therfore we muſt either take the deuilles counſail, and ſo diſtruſting the might &amp; merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouidence of God, make ſtones, ſtockes, and idolatrous popiſhe Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, bread to poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues withall: or throwe our ſelues downe headlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g from the highe pynnacle of Goddes temple the celeſtial Ieruſalem in to the botomles pitte of all errous, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie and hell: or fall to the deuilles fete, and take him for our good Lorde. Or elles contrary wiſe ſticking faſt
<pb facs="tcp:13791:37"/>
to the ſcriptures and goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, bidde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, auaunt Satan, with all his mummyng. Maſſes and ſtyncking ſuperſticion. We wyll non of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though we neuer haue breade, &amp; though we be torne in pieces for it.</p>
            <p>Euery cowherde will (for couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wages and fee) be glad to be reteyned in gariſon, and ſet the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter legge before (as though he wolde be a good ſouldiour) while no daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gier of batail is at hande, and while ther is peace, &amp; take all one parte. And ſo in bleſſed king Edwardes daies, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery wan (almoſt) pretended frende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip &amp; forewardeneſſe to the doctrine of the goſpell, and engliſhe churche ſeruice, ſeing the Magiſtrates &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude layne to that ſyde: ſome of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſom of flattery, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt men for the commodious gayne that they founde by churche landes &amp; goodes, not mynding to amende their lyues towardes God by the goſpel, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour therof to augment their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinges and pelfe in this worlde.</p>
            <p>But like as if a ſouldiour ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the armye of his ſouerayne liege Lord to the enemies ſide (although he ſaye, his harte was with his ſoueraine ſtil,
<pb facs="tcp:13791:38"/>
and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ranne awaye only for feare) muſt nedes be demed a traitour, a cowhearde, and rennagate: euen ſo ſhal euery one that profeſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name and religion of Chriſt, to be one of his ſouldiours (for our life is a very war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare vpon earthe) be demed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicte of highe treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt his moſt natural ſouerayne liege Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, king of all kinges, which in tyme of his ſpirituall warres for the goſpelles ſake, renneth awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſtandarde and gariſon in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuilles campe, to take parte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> popiſhe maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, the moſt deadly foes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes goſpell and bloodſhead.</p>
            <p>Now is the fielde pitched, now our enemies bende their ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt vs face to face, now they ſee the campe of goſpellers weakened and lye open vnto their municiones. They ſee ſom fall to their ſide, ſom ſpeake faire, ſom diſſemble, and fewe are glad to abide the bickering, &amp; that maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cruell papiſtes to make ſo thicke Laru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, and to com on ſo luſtily w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their hotte ſkyrmiſhes on euery ſide againſt Chriſt our captai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; al his armye roial Howbeit ſeing Chriſt hathe the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, and ſhall make al his enemies
<pb facs="tcp:13791:38"/>
his foote ſtole: and ſeing alſo he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth patentes of ſo large honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fee &amp; wages to ſuch his ſouldiours, as by pacient ſuffring of perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtande ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fully to his ſtandarde, and abyde the ende of the fraye: as he by his heraulde of armes, thapoſtle Paule maketh open proclamacion in his coate armour, ſayeng: Yf we dye with Chriſt here, we ſhall lyue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> euerlaſtingly: Yf we ſuffre with him here, we ſhall reigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glorious heauenly kingdom.</p>
            <p>And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary parte, foraſmuche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame proclamacion declareth the payne of ſuche of vs, as re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtes enſigne or ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darde, ſayeng: Yf we denye or forſake him, he wil alſo denye &amp; forſake vs. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> general muſtre and paye daye cometh (wher the conſtaunt ſouldiours ſhal be crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with glorie and honour in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal heauenly kingdom) Chriſt the captain and iudge ſhal ſaye vnto ſuche ſhrinking traytours and cowheardly rennagates:</p>
            <p>Auaunt you workers of wickedneſſe I knowe yow not. Get you hence you curſed in to euerlaſting fyre, which is <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared for the deuil and his angelles.
<pb facs="tcp:13791:39"/>
I thinke therfore it is neceſſary good and very highe tyme for vs, to arme our ſelues cappe a pee (as the ſame Heraulde of armes Paule commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs in king Ieſus name, Ephe. 6.) and for our owne ſauegarde &amp; vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to kepe batail raye through per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecucions, troubles, rebukes and ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the worlde, and folowe the ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darde of Chriſtes bloody croſſe luſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to beſtere vs like tall felowes, in mortifieng our owne fleſhe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally hauing before our eies the fore rennyng example and viewe, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all the martirs and confeſſours that haue ben ſouldiours of the ſame bande, and ſkyrmiſhed in their owne blood from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of Abel vnto theſe daies: but alſo the preſent conſtaunt courage of the moſt faithfull ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of Chriſt, Thomas Cranmere Arrchbiſhop of Cantorbury. Hugh La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer, Micholas Riddley, Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Robert ferrar, Rolande Tailour, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rogers, Laurence Gaunders, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bradforde, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Filpotte, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Glouer, and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cardemaker with many other bothe men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which did boldly in ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſpleaye Chriſtes hanner in the myddes of his
<pb facs="tcp:13791:39"/>
enemies, and willingly haue ſheadde their blood for the ſalekeping of their forte, I meane for the defenſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes inuincible goſpell: as well to the great comforte and encorageing of the reſt of Chriſtes armye, as to the confuſion and vaynquiſhing of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt with all his blood thirſtie ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelinges and maſſemonging kyndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, for all their prowde bragges and impudent ruſting.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe how faynt and how weake a ſouldiour I my ſelf haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this behalfe, myne owne experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (at my furſt entrie in to the goſpel) taught me .x. or .xi. yeares agoo. By reaſon wherof being afrayed of mine owne weakeneſſe, &amp; partly being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced from my vicarage by malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous force &amp; rage of ſome vnthankeful people, ꝑtly bycauſe I was laid wayte for by writtes, proceſſes, and cruell threateninges of D. Ermeſtede &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain other traiterous harted papiſtes (which recanted their errours &amp; pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges viſitacion) but chiefly being loth to fal in to myne enemies handes, for feare of blaſphemyng the truthe, by reaſon of myne owne ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful weakeneſſe, or rigorous enpriſon
<pb facs="tcp:13791:40"/>
ment, I departed from my vicarage ſomwhat before extreme trouble came. And albeit I did confirme this doctrine of faithe in ſondry ſermones within my pariſhe, in that rude ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geing tempeſt, &amp; offred to haue done the like in other great pariſhes ther about, where they durſt not receaue me: yet myne owne conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce accuſeth me, for that I taried not ther ſtill to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermoſt. And therfore if that haue ben any occaſion of offence or ſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke to any of Chriſtes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion (as I truſt it hathe not) I moſt hartily heſeche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to forgeue me that weake wickedneſſe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked weakeneſſe.</p>
            <p>And like as it hathe pleaſed God of his merciful goodneſſe to holde me ſtill in the confeſſion of the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failing truthe, that I taught priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely &amp; openly in thoſe parties, during the tyme of my miniſterie: euen ſo I truſt he will graunt me the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of this faithe vnto the ende (the rather at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>placion of your good hartie prayers) &amp; grace to ſeke only his glorie to the comforte of his poore afflicted flocke, with that litel talent that he hathe lent me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:40"/>
And if it be his godly pleaſure to caſt me in to his enemies handes, I truſt he will alſo geue me will and ſtreynght manfully and ioyfully to geue my life for the confirmacion of this my faithe.</p>
            <p>Now for a farewell, I beſeche you alſo good brothren, praye (after your wonted maner) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercie ſeate of God, that it wolde pleaſe him, to defende and encreace his churche: to graunt his goſpel a ioyful free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and proſperous ſucceſſe through out the hole worlde: to holde his merci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful hande of proteccion ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme of Englande: to geue vs true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and to forgeue vs all our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: to ſuccour, helpe &amp; comforte all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in daungier, neceſſitie, trouble, erile or in ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for his glorious goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and wordes ſake: to bring in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye of truthe al ſuche as haue erred and are deceaued: to forgeue our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, perſecutours &amp; ſlaunderours, &amp; to turne their hartes: to ſtreynghten ſuche as doo ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, to comforte &amp; helpe the weake harted, to raiſe vp them that fall, and ſhortly to treade downe the deuil vnder our fete: and with his almighty power, to deſtroye
<pb facs="tcp:13791:41"/>
Antichriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al his ſwarme of ſhaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges &amp; curſed kingdom: And finally to haue mercie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all men: Amen.</p>
            <p>Good brothren, I beſeche you by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercifulneſſe of God, forgeue one an other, loue one an other, beare one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an other, cheariſhe one an other, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte one an other, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſorte one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; (to your power) helpe one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo as we maye in the myddes of this rageing tempeſt &amp; ſkyrmyſhe of perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in faithe by the holy gooſt, ioyfully loking for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great God, &amp; our ſaueour Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; finally to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laude &amp; glorie of his grace amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the righteous, which ſhal ſhyne like the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the merites of his only deare ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, brother, &amp; euerlaſting ſaueour. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther &amp; the holy gooſt, be al glorie, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; praiſe, now and for euermore worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ende. Amen. And in the ſame one immortal, almightie God, I bid you al moſt hartily wel to fare.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poore ſeruaunt in the Lorde. Io. Olde.</signed>
               <pb facs="tcp:13791:41"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
